

Uzmar de Jesús Gómez Yáñez

CURRICULUM VITAE



Detailed List of Grades

MSc Scientific Computing and Data Analysis

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Learned to program throughout the Physics career, mainly in scientific computing topics. Hands-on experience applying Machine Learning algorithms to real business problems. Excellent usage of GNU / Linux systems and knowledge of object-oriented programming languages such as Python and C++. I have also worked in the academic field as a teacher assistant, teaching mathematics, computer science, physics and other topics at a university level. Good understanding of algorithms, data structures, bayesian statistics and its relation with machine learning.

PERSONAL DATA

ADDRESS: Durham, England PHONE: +44 7704 613361

EMAIL: uzmar.gomez@ciencias.unam.mx
LINKEDIN: www.linkedin.com/in/uzmargomez
GITHUB: https://github.com/uzmargomez

EDUCATION

PRESENT | MSc in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis, Department of Computer Science, Durham University,

Durham, United Kingdom.

2021 | Specialization: Earth and Environmental Sciences

OVERALL SCORE: -

2018 | BSc in Physics, Faculty of Science, National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Mexico City,

Mexico.

2011 Thesis: "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric"

Description: Creation of a finite differences scheme that evolves the relativistic Vlasov equation on a

black hole metric background, assuming this is an advective equation, with velocities

dependent both on time and position.

Advisor: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

OVERALL SCORE: 9.37/10 Detailed List of Grades

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming Languages | Python, C/C++, Fortran, Julia, Go

Machine/Deep Learning | TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, Facebook Prophet, ARIMA, SARIMA, LDA, PCA,

Kmeans, KNN, Neuranl Networks, Recommendation systems, Classification

problems

Serving Seldon Core, TFServing
Databases SQL, MongoDB
Containers Docker, Kubernetes

Operating Systems | Debian GNU/Linux, Ubuntu GNU/Linux, Windows

Web Backend | Flask

Web Frontend | HTML, Bootstrap

Version Control | Git

Parallel Computing CUDA C/C++, CUDA Python Data Visualization Plotly Dash, Qlik, Tableau

GCP Tools (Console and CLI)

BigQuery, BQ ML, Compute Engine, Composer, Artifact Registry, Kubernetes
Engine, Storage, Data Studio, Kubeflow, Data Fusion, Cloud Build, VertexAI

LANGUAGES

ENGLISH: C1 Level - IELTS (2021)
SPANISH: Mothertongue

FRENCH: Basic

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

Academic

Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Numerical Analysis, General Relativity, Numerical Relativity, Black Holes.

Non academic

Science Fiction and Fantasy Reading, Running, Swimming, Playing the Guitar, Traveling, Videogames.

EXPERIENCE

Short Description

Jul 2020 - Jan 2022. Data Scientist at Rackspace Technology. I helped on the migration of data from on-premises servers to the GCP cloud. I worked on a churn prediction model that uses features related to the COVID19 spreading aside from other business-related features to predict customer attrition, this work includes the development of the model using XGBoost, as well as the deployment of it using Kubeflow and the serving via Seldon Core. I was also involved in constructing an SSAS OLAP Cube to be used by the company for inventory-related queries. I worked on NLP tasks, such as the extraction of themes out of tickets using semantic similarity, by getting embeddings vectors out of sentences with a transformer architecture named Universal Sentence Encoder. Worked on how to translate voice to text. I built two production-level applications using Plotly Dash.

Dec 2019 - Jun 2020. Data Scientist at Softtek. I worked on a face recognition system using a method called Sparse Representation and another one using Neural Networks. I acquired a deep understanding of Neural Networks for Face Detection and Recognition, Image Classification, Language Processing, among others, as well as some experience in Data Visualization tools such as Tableau.

Sep 2019 - Dec 2019. Data Scientist Trainee at Softtek. I learned about different statistical and machine learning techniques, as well as algorithms, to study a wide variety of problems.

2016 - 2019. As mentioned below, I have taught Computer Science classes, in which the Python programming language was introduced to Physics students.

Sep 2018 - Dec 2019. I have research experience using the Einstein Toolkit, a software platform created for supporting research in relativistic astrophysics and gravitational physics.

Subjects I have taught:

- Computer Science.
 https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/102.pdf
- Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation 1. https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/docencia/horarios/presentacion/295997
- Relativity
 https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/718.pdf
- Mathematics I for Applied Sciences. http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1118.pdf
- Mathematics II for Applied Sciences. http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1216.pdf

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

Present	Volunteer
JAN 2022	Durham Foodbank
DEC 2021	Teacher
Jun 2021	Casa de la Sal
	Support children with HIV on various Mathematics and English Language assignments.
SEP 2019	Teacher
Mar 2019	University Student Council (CEU México)
	Provide tools to university students to help develop their academic, professional and personal skills, to facilitate their employment and the definition of their life project.
MAR 2019	Volunteer
SEP 2018	Adopt a Talent Program (PAUTA)
	Encourage scientific vocation so that those children and adolescents who like science and have outstanding skills, find a space where they can share their interest and learn from each other.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

SEP 2019	Fellow
JAN 2017	Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves (Red ANyOG, CONACYT).
DEC 2019	Student Associate
JAN 2016	Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.
Jan 2016	Student Associate
JAN 2015	Institute of Physics, UNAM.

PRESENTATIONS AND POSTER SESSIONS

OCT 11, 2017	Poster Presentation at LX NATIONAL CONGRESS OF PHYSICS.
	Monterrey, Mexico
	Presentation of a poster about my undergraduate thesis "Numerical Study of Vlasov
	Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric".

SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONORS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

I	Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Proyect Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT).
	Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Undergraduate School Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT).

REFERENCES

NAME: Dr. Charles Mueller
OCCUPATION: Senior Engineer at Amazon

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/charles-n-mueller/

NAME: Dr. Fernando Herrera

OCCUPATION: Senior Data Engineer at Revolut

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/fernando-jose-herrera-elizalde-76a32790/

NAME: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

Institution Name: Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

OCCUPATION: Director, Researcher, Teacher malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx